Okay, let's see how nativeorn Americans
were handling the huge waves of
immigrants that arrived in the United
States during the Gilded Age. And
spoiler alert, it's not great. Anyway,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, so let's
start with a brief reminder of what's
going on with immigration during the
Gilded Age. So, as I mentioned in the
last video, immigrants from all over the
world were pouring forth onto America's
shores in the last few decades of the
19th century, and they largely settled
in urban industrial cities where the
jobs were most abundant. And despite the
fact that many immigrants found each
other and lived together in urban
neighborhoods where they attempted to
uphold their cultural traditions, there
was enormous pressure to assimilate to
American culture. Well, they don't look
American. They don't act American. They
sure as Moses don't speak American. And
so many nativeorn Americans began to
grow concerned over the identity of
America with all these non-Americans
running around. Now, the most popular
metaphor for immigrant assimilation was
the melting pot, which came from a play
of the same name written by an English
Jew named Israel Zangil. The idea was
that people of very different
backgrounds would enter the melting pot
of the United States and come out
indistinguishable from nativeborn
American citizens. And while that was a
nice idea that stirs up all the warm
fuzzies, the melting pot was more of an
ideal and less of an accurate reflection
of reality. No, in most cases,
immigrants assimilated to a degree, but
they also worked to keep their
traditions and languages alive in their
new home. So, in that case, immigrants
were more like a vegetable soup than a
melting pot. Yes, they made their lives
in the broth of American culture, but
they still maintain much of their own
unique cultural distinction. And that
got nativeborn Americans more than a
little twitch. And in a moment, I'll
explore the juicy details of that
twitchiness. But first, let me mention
that if you need help getting an A in
your class and a five on your exam in
May, then you might want to check out my
A Push Heimler review guide. It is the
fastest way to study and guaranteed to
be the sassiest review product on the
market. So, get that clicky finger out
and check that link in the description.
And now, I reckon it's time to stir up
some drama. So, let's talk about the
various responses to this influx of
immigrants. Now, to be clear, in the
1860s, many wealthy industrialists with
support from federal laws welcomed this
wave of immigrants from Europe and Asia
since they provided an enormous low-wage
labor pool who could work in their
factories. Like, there were plenty of
low-wage jobs that native-born Americans
weren't keen on filling anyway. And so,
industrialists were all kinds of giddy
about these immigrants coming to work
for them. But here's where I tell you
that by the 1880s, the overwhelming
number of foreign immigrants in America
sparked a public debate about whether
the United States should continue to
welcome them or refuse them entry. And
I'll give you an example of both sides
of this debate with respect to Chinese
immigrants. So Chinese immigrants began
arriving in significant numbers during
the California Gold Rush and then
transition to providing essential labor
in the West during the construction of
the transcontinental railroads. And by
1852 something like 20,000 Chinese
people were living in California. And by
1870 it was over 50,000. But then the
panic of 1873 hit and that economic
downturn inspired white workers to
scapegoat Chinese workers for their own
miseries. Like the white workers argue
that the Chinese immigrants were
stealing their jobs since the Chinese
would work for so much less. And you
know, there's some truth to that, but
for the most part, it was pretty
performative since the white people
didn't even want those jobs to begin
with. And so, the rise of anti-Chinese
sentiment in the West put pressure on
Congress to address the issue. And they
responded with the Chinese Exclusion Act
of 1882. And that law is exactly what it
sounds like. It enacted a complete ban
on any further Chinese immigration. And
it forbade current Chinese people in
America from becoming citizens. And just
for poops and giggles, you should know
that this policy represented the first
US law to target a specific racial group
and therefore provided a precedent for
future race-based laws. Okay. Now, the
other side of the debate here was taken
up by Chinese immigrants themselves. For
example, in 1898, the Supreme Court
handed down a landmark decision in the
United States v. Wong Kim Arc.
Basically, Wong Kim Arc, whose parents
were Chinese immigrants, was born in San
Francisco in 1873 before the Chinese
Exclusion Act had been passed. But in
the 1880s, Wong traveled outside the US
and was denied re-entry based on the
prohibitions of that law. Therefore,
Wong challenged this development in
court and argued that based on the
birthright citizenship clause of the
14th amendment that his birth on
American soil made him an American
citizen. And hold on to your butts
because the court actually agreed and
this decision provided an important
precedent in the interpretation of the
14th amendment's birthright citizenship
clause. I mean, can we just appreciate
for a second how crazy that decision
was? Like in the 19th century,
anti-Chinese sentiment was at its peak
and racism was largely accepted and
perpetuated. And it was in that
environment that the court ruled that
babies born to the hated Chinese
immigrants were to be considered
full-fledged American citizens. What?
But it wasn't just Chinese immigrants
who sparked this debate. No, in one way
or another, almost all the major groups
of immigrants got the nivist treatment
during this time as well. Now nativism
when being defined is essentially a
policy of protecting the interest of
nativeborn folks over against the
interest of immigrants. And nivism
reached a fever pitch in the hands of
Protestant ministers like Henry Kat
Lodge who argued that white Anglo-Saxon
Americans were committing and I quote
race suicide by allowing so many members
of inferior races to intermingle with
pure-blooded Americans. Additionally,
nivists formed groups like the American
Protective Association, which was a
powerful organization against Catholics
aimed at curtailing the growing
influence of Irish Catholics in local
politics. And I could go on, but now
let's turn the corner so I can tell you
about an ideology that made this
widespread immigrant hatefest a reality.
And that nasty ideology is known as
social Darwinis. Now, in this period,
the social sciences emerged as a new
form of academic study. And sociologists
soon made attempts to explain the
features of the increasing complexities
of human society. Now in 1859, Charles
Darwin published his groundbreaking
scientific work on the origin of
species. So the book laid out his theory
of biological evolution which argue that
the species which survive and thrive do
so because they are better adapted to
their environment. On the flip side,
those species which do not survive
perish because they will not or cannot
adapt to changing environmental
conditions. And to be clear, Darwin used
this theory to explain changes in birds
and flowers and honey badgers and human
beings in the biological sense. But it
wasn't long before social scientists
like the British philosopher Herbert
Spencer began applying these biological
principles to explain the development of
human society. And so Spencer was all
like, hm, if only the fittest survive in
nature, wouldn't that also be true
[snorts] in society? Now later this
ideology became known as social
Darwinism. And American commentators
like William Graham Sumner used it to
explain and more to the point to justify
the profound inequalities of an
industrializing America. In other words,
according to Sumar, the reason the
industrialists at the top of the heap
were so rich and powerful is because
they had adapted well to the new social
and economic environment. But the reason
that immigrants are poor and live in
squalor is because they have not adapted
to the environment. And in nature, when
a species hasn't adapted to the
environment, they just die out so that
the stronger species can flourish. Like
it would be altogether dumb to try to
help a species survive that no longer
has the biological makeup to live in a
changing environment. And that idea
applied to social inequality in the
guilded age had a way of preventing
those in the halls of power from working
to alleviate the suffering of what they
considered a weaker species. However,
despite the fact that powerful Americans
were getting drunk on such philosophies
and toasting their own fitness to
survive, there were some Americans who
worked to help immigrants assimilate to
society. And one of the most significant
movements in this respect was the
establishment of settlement houses which
helped immigrants to adapt to US customs
and language. For example, Jane Adams
founded the whole house in Chicago,
which offered a variety of services to
immigrants, including English classes
and vocational training and medical
help. They also worked to help
immigrants succeed in the workplace by
offering child care services and
building parks and playgrounds for the
children. Or another example was the
Hyram House in Cleveland, Ohio, which
was established in a densely populated
Irish neighborhood. It began as an
institution to help immigrants study for
and pass their citizenship exams, but
its mission soon expanded to offer a
multitude of services for immigrants,
including a kindergarten and summer camp
and vocational training as well. So yes,
no doubt nivism made the lives of
immigrants far more difficult, but there
were also helpers along the way. And
those helpers, mostly middle-class and
upper class women, would go on to
channel those impulses for reform into
many other causes in the 19th and 20th
centuries. However, I should also
mention that many of these reformers
also acted because they were concerned
about the influence of immigrant culture
on their own culture and therefore
wanted to assimilate the newcomers by
exposing them to what they called
civilizing influences. So, it's a mixed
bag. Okay, you can click here to watch
my other unit 6 videos, or you can click
here to grab my Heimler review guide,
which is going to help you get an A in
your class and a five on your exam in
May. I'm glad you stopped by, and I'll
catch you on the flip-flop.